So this is the saba suta.
The blessed one said what is the orb?
Simply the eye and forms,
ear and sounds, nose and smells, tongue,
flavor, body and touches, and mano and dhamas.
body and touches, and mano and dhamas.
So mano, intellect,
intellect. Yeah.
And dharmas, images,
images, phenomena,
thoughts, thoughts. Sure.
So the intellect and thoughts
this monk is called the all.
Anyone who would say rejecting this all
I will make known another
all. Yeah.
Yeah.
A new all.
I will describe another one something
a higher reality than this.
Yeah. Yeah.
Yeah.
If questioned on what exactly might be
the grounds for your statement, he would
be unable to explain and furthermore get
frustrated. Why? Because that is not his domain.
Why? Because that is not his domain.
It's not his personal scope. He he
cannot know that. H
well whatever that new old he might be
describing it will be within any one of
those cannot be anything apart from the
six sense space inconceivable when you
say no no no this is apart from it well
you're just describing another image to
me that is part of it
I can describe another all that I
that you believe
you believe in imagine
ignoring the fact that exactly you
imagine it is it that it's a real as
imagination sure as images as phenomena
it is And thus it's very much within
this all.
But you claiming that it's beyond the
six senses while using the six senses to
describe it and refer to it or even just
think of it. Well, that's a
contradiction in terms for that very
reason. How can you then designate the O
if you can't even think it?
What are you designating? What are you
talking about?
That's what people say like well you
know you can't you can't really describe
God it's like well you just described it
that's exactly a description oh it's
unescribable oh that's a property of God which is
oh that's a property of God which is
then describable
so then it's a contradiction in terms
such a statement
so we got that that common view which is
there is something beyond All the
aggregates. Yeah.
Yeah.
You know that that ground of being that
unity of
self, unity of self.
unity of self.
Exactly.
That Yeah. One non non-dual I suppose.
U consciousness
that never changes.
Yeah. All the names you can.
All the names you can.
But how do you know that?
Cuz you have images of it.
Yeah. Cuz I have a thought.
Which are changing. which is a
yeah so I'm still stuck. You're ignoring
what's right in front of you and
reinterpreting everything from this
internal obviously you cannot be outside
of your aggregates but externally
assumed universe and world and point of view and
universe and world and point of view and
in a nutshell that's definition of
assuming that you can be out don't
matter what view you have what
interpretation what description whether
you're talking about anicha or the
universal atman it doesn't matter if
there is an attitude of from the outside
that's even if you don't think necessarily in
even if you don't think necessarily in
terms of self
unique independent
means basically outside point of view
and that's an internal image
which you realize oh that's why it's a
contradiction in terms
so whenever you think outside it's done
with mano and intellect which is six
sense basis which means it's inside of
this hole
so is there a thing beyond the
aggregates or beyond experience
And you just answer no it's there's
nothing like that.
No, see that's already there's nothing.
Sorry. Yeah.
You just made it into something.
Yeah. Theoretically there is nothing.
Theoretically there is nothing.
But you have to realize
that you like theory it's always going
to be on a level of a view. So you can
have the right theory but even then it
will remain on the level of a view which
means it's not true for you. You need to
start doing it. So when you make a I
must never make a statement that is
nothing. No make a statement that is
nothing but then include it rightly in
the all that is here and now and that is
your practice that is your ba that is
your right order right contradict your
right um rightly arrange things that
will be then freeing you from these
contradictions assumptions.
assumptions.
Yeah yeah yeah every assumption is has
to be a contradiction in itself. Not
that you necessarily see it that way
initially but that's the whole point.
assumption of external self, assumption
of the views coming like as the as the
determining factor for everything else
ignoring the reality upon which they
exist.
So you I can have an imagination a
fantastic imagination of consciousness
some some light or whatever some image
of the ground of being or whatever
and then I can just
devote myself to that and abandon all of
this lesser stuff. lesser stuff.
Sure.
Lesser consciousnesses.
Sure. Whatever. And you know get quite far and
Whatever. And you know get quite far and
you know free from sensuality.
Sure. Supposedly. Yeah. I mean if you
really commit to it again not to the
image necessarily like image on its own
will not free you from sensuality but if
on account of that image even if it's to
to to some extent contradictory you do
start living withdrawn from the senses
in the solitude contemplating lack of
satisfaction then you will abandon
sensuality even without the right view
and without the Buddhist teaching but
not without the work
and like we said
there's difference between abandoning
sensuality in replacing it with a higher
reward that's not abandoning.
Yeah. You see that's the thing. So if I
but what I'm saying is it is possible
to actually abandon sensuality. The
Buddhist said that in the s as well you
can approve the assumption of sensuality
undo that contradiction even outside of
the Buddhist teaching.
But but the work needs to be done not like
but the work needs to be done not like
on account of some divine kind of
providence descending upon you and
suddenly you're just free. No, no, no.
Like if monks and nuns or practices
other practices summon as brahinss of
other religions free themselves from
sensuality it had to have been the same
way of gradual training unintentionally
withdrawal guarding of the sense living
in the seclusion and really experiencing
that self-loathing on the level of the
presence of the body and the aggregates
that they do not want but not act out of
it to destroy it or go back to
sensuality and that is the first Janna
Now sure they might have had all sorts
of other views
uh that would then not necessarily make
them value it the way they should but
factually they could have uprooted the
the sensual desire the assumption of
beautiful in the senses and in the body.
So a person can still have like the love
of God.
Yeah. Sorry,
but they would have they could have if
they applied if they actually endured
withdraw from from the senses from the
unh wholesome states complete
relinquishing any perception of form
that they have as in relinquish the
ownership and delight in it. Yeah, they
could have experienced the release on
account of it because the mind has been
become de has been developed in regard
to their own body.
But in it's like when the Buddha said
that he wasn't perfectly celibate, you
know, till he gave up even the the
well from the dharma point of view now.
Yeah. Yeah. But he gave up sensuality. Sure.
Yeah. But he gave up sensuality. Sure.
But he extended that for the future
rebirth. See, you gave up sensuality
here. You haven't you're not free from
samsara which means
you can go back to like whatever
heavenly but when that runs out
you're back to centrality and back to
other things.
So yeah you want to be perfectly
celibate perfectly withdrawn as in never
even return to it. Doesn't matter how
many years ahead you might spend in the
he in heaven doesn't matter you never
return sensuality well for that you need
the right view that's anam
person free from sensuality with the
right view is and he's called non
returner for that very reason.
So the thing that distinguishes
somebody who's given up sensuality
um
uh with atavvada and somebody who's
um given up atavvada um so we were
talking about images and dharmas. Um
Uhhuh. So you were saying like somebody might
So you were saying like somebody might
give up sensuality on account of some
image of a god or that they were devoted
to that they valued more than sensuality
or
again that's not giving up though they
might be
that's replacing it with
Yeah. Yeah. That's more like you just
replace one intoxication with another.
So it's not but what I'm saying is and
and the Buddha himself said that when
people ask him how what do we practice
in order to be reborn in Brahma world or
two heavens and he was well you practice
uh perfect sort of celibacy not giving
into sensual thoughts and so on and
these heavens will be guaranteed for you
I don't know which specifically but that
was kind of the gist of it the point
being yes there is that mundane sort of
you just replace one intoxication with
another that's not uprooting sensuality
but somebody can on account of their
belief and the view in God or atman or
whatever actually do the work on the
physical level and keep the precepts be
completely withdrawn from the s
sensuality uh guard of the sensors live
in seclusion
experience that that that as I call
existential pathigo of the senses there
that are now being withdrawn and tamed
basically go through withdrawals
That's that self-loading in that
practice sense. Um the mind will have to
come down if they don't give it up.
And when the mind comes down, they will
then realize, oh, you know, this is
actually more valuable. This is safer.
This is more peaceful. This is less
disturbing than sensual pursuits and
factually lose desire towards sensual
pleasures. Free. We free from that
assumption that they are actually
pleasant. that these burning charcoal
embers are pleasant
without still on the basis of that wrong
notion of the eternal self or whatever
but not oh on account of an image they
give it up no on account of an image
they might actually do the work and it's
the work that will free them
yeah yeah yeah because it's implicit
anyway this idea of
that's why I always ask people ask you
as well like oh how did you start you
know what was your first
but I mean it doesn't apply just to
other practices and religions applies to
even Buddhist practices today. It was
like sure what what whatever instruction
do you follow whether it's for Janna or
for this or for that whoever instructed
you whatever you learned it from did it
emphasize the the necessity of gradual training of
the the necessity of gradual training of
withdrawal of guarding of the senses of
taming of the mind
and you realize that 99% think no it
goes straight into the view straight
into images straight into the pictures
and this is what what it is and this is
what it will be and then you just okay
I'll just go straight there cuz that's
what I'm presented here.
So often you will be like oh yeah it's
great. Oh yeah there's this virtue and
precepts. I mean the sutas talk about it
but no yeah I I understand this. Oh yeah
the janna and this great fine I'll just
go straight there. So people completely
neglect and ignore or put aside or do it
kind of second best kind of as an
afterthought the precepts and guarding
of the sense and they think their
commitment to a view the image
information is how you progress.
Now you can have literally you can have
the image of some random dity but if you
do the work on account of it you'll be
free from sensuality and then you
realize oh but that's why I'm free.
You still might have your beliefs in
your daties and so on, but you will know
where the freedom came from.
You will know where the drying up and
taming of the senses came from.
Might as well skip the deity and say
just this.
Well, then I think you would obviously
be much in much more favorable position
to to re-evaluate your beliefs and your
daties because you're not being
obstructed by sensual desires and
projections. That's why even somebody
with the wrong view who has went through
like guarding of the sensor and not
given it up keeping the precepts they
actually factually have diminished the
amount of dust in their eyes. So when
then they would hear the Buddha they
would be oh wow but that's it because
they already have the ingredients for it
more or less they're already there in a
sense of their perspective is seriously
unpolluted now because they have
withdrawn from sensuality
and they were I mean the fire
worshippers the whatever else those the
500 disciples when they came and then
completely different practices but they
were obviously tamed physically the
senses were properly developed the mind
was developed in regard to the senses
So although it was a completely
different view of what the practice is
and where the value is when they heard
the Buddha they all oh okay let us all
become monks now this is it.
Yeah they understood it instantaneously
but that is against the background of
India being generally quite valuing
aestheticism and if we see like the
deities and the practices
the way they are presented nowadays
well it seems to me that is quite
different. So this is useful to make
that distinction.
Yeah, that's what I'm saying. The reason
they understood it, it's not because
their daties made them understand
completely different practice that
negates those deities. It was because
their deities whatever they still
actually practiced withdrawal.
Yeah. From the senses they were they were
From the senses they were they were
celibate. They were taming guarding of
the sense the whole thing.
Mhm. The mind will have to clean up.
The mind will have to clean up.
Yeah. Yeah.
So whatever teaching do you follow?
Well, ask yourself, okay, but does he go
straight into the the the the images,
the view, the expectations, the
pleasure, the joy, the the joy, the
happiness, the Janna, the Janna. Yeah,
you read the sutras for that Janna. Do
you do everything else beforehand? Or do
you just go straight to the pity, just
the pity? It's just everything is just
blissful because that's what my
meditation is.
Well, that's not the meditation that the
Buddha was talking about ever.
Yeah, bliss will come, but obviously of
a very different kind.
Yeah. And then again, even if say, well,
I don't I don't believe in any of that.
I don't I don't think it's necessary. I
just have the view of the instruction
and it works for me. What what do you
have to lose if you keep the precepts
and God sends those so you don't have to
I'm not asking you to give up whatever
view. I'm not saying all these views are
wrong or whatever else. So just
objectively, rationally, what do you
have to lose? Well, the pleasure that is
ra the senses.
Oh, you mean the pleasure opposite of
Janna. You still don't want to give up
while you want the pleasure of Janna.
And that's exactly it. So, it's like, oh
yeah, what what do I have to lose if I'm
if I actually do follow what the suts
say? I don't need to give up my Janna
practice or whatever else. But yeah, why
don't I take the precepts seriously? Be
celibate. God descends those. Leave it.
I mean I can then have like Janna on
steroids because you know if I obviously
have a view that I can have Janna while
I'm steep in sensuality.
Imagine the Janna that the Buddha was
talking about the Janna when you
withdrawn from everything on wholesome.
So there you go. Use your sensual desire
for your Janna and actually do it
properly. Get get do it the proper way.
Yeah.
Now, is there a practical way to discern
the all without making the wrong move of
trying to look at it from outside?
So, so, so how is the all being
or rather there is a practical way but
not without making a move from the
outside. Yeah, exactly. That's the point.
Yeah, exactly. That's the point.
It's learning how to correctly recollect
in regard to the move from the outside
that you already made.
Uhhuh. In other words, learning how to include
In other words, learning how to include
what you excluded. And that is how you
discern from
that is how you will eventually find a
balance and stop spilling outside for a
and stop spilling outside for a
standpoint.
But it's it's it's a it's a it's a it's
a like a training process of training
your mind to that spillage of outside
view reflexively reinclude it. But obviously
reflexively reinclude it. But obviously
you're going to reinclude it too much.
So then that will become your outside
view. And then you include that and you
do it for as long as the mind doesn't
calm down within that.
That's almost a description of
developing. That's exactly what it is.
That's exactly what it is.
Yeah.
Whose description?
Well, what we were talking about the
other day.
My description. Yeah. I thought, oh, who
described that? That's that's a good
description. No, that's exactly what it
is. Yeah. Yum. That's exactly what it
is. that being able to to to establish that
that being able to to to establish that
balance which again whoever tries it
they're going to arrive they're going to
try and establish it from that
standpoint it won't be the balance but you include
it won't be the balance but you include
a standpoint okay that's already
temporary balance then you exclude you
again assume the external point of view
or this is it you include that to that
extent there is a balance up until the
balance remains whether you include or
exclude the balance remains
and that's where you know like okay
Yeah. So I stopped assuming outside
because even the thoughts of outside
it's just I cannot doubt that they're
not outside and even saying that there's
not outside I cannot even imply that
there could be some other outside.
Yeah. Any thought any image is understood in
Any thought any image is understood in
its own nature as being there inside for
what it is
that has to result in the noble right
view which is precisely the the seeing
well the uprooting of the art.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So when there is
no more um when you're incapable of u
you can have thoughts of outside but
they don't carry the same assumption the
weight of actually being outside
of actually being outside
you're not following that
it's just it's just an image you still
see there's an image of outside so it's
like a relative outside there is no
belief behind that it's an outside of
this whole thing
uh and then yeah then there is no
moratavada
and that's exactly what that person
could also become incapable
on develop on depending on what is
perceived as an outside form, duty,
necessity, inconceivable. They cannot even conceive
inconceivable. They cannot even conceive
that as relevant anymore because they're
not out there anymore. There is no more
atavada. So there is no more you know
like how people take for weight of
tradition for granted or many do it thus
it's right. Thus it must be done.
Yeah. Yeah. That is about
it's a public view. It's a view of that
public world where value comes by all us
doing it.
Uhhuh. And and that one free fromada is
And and that one free fromada is
incapable of thinking that.
So was it Rome alone? Rome alone. Rome
alone like a rhinoceros horn.
Uhhuh. I've gone beyond the witherings of the
I've gone beyond the witherings of the
view. That verse.
Uhhuh. Yeah. Yeah.
Nobody can be my guide. Ro Rome alone
like a rhinoceros horn.
Yeah. as in sana who has understood this
it's just incon not like nobody can be
my guide I'm the best no it's just
inconceivable because see others are perceived as the
because see others are perceived as the
external selves to my external already
but if that fundamental is gone the
external selves of other people is also
gone that yeah
that yeah
the external extent of theirelves let's
put it that way
so the weight of million people doing
something is meaningless you will do it
because it's aligned with Dharma or not
align with the dharma, you won't do it.
That's equally within. Yeah.
Yeah. Yeah.
And sensuality, ill will, distraction
cause one to
to lose that perspective. Acting out of
these things because
uh well acting out causes one to lose
perspective. I mean, they're there and you don't act
I mean, they're there and you don't act
out of them, then you're seeing them for
what they are. So that you're not losing
perspective. Yeah. So there might still be arising
Yeah. So there might still be arising
for somebody who is not free from them,
but you realize that that's in in and of
itself it's not an impediment.
Exactly. Like what is an impediment is when you
Like what is an impediment is when you
wrongly attend to it, act out of it, try
to get rid of it, are averse towards it
or or delighting in it.
Or that's that's what's going to
maintain it.
You can sort of yeah have a mood there
and if you're not acting out of it,
you're you're seeing it for what it is.
Yeah. Then it's kind of all right. It's
like yeah I mean
well it came on its own. It will go on
its own. You realize oh this is the the
my responsibility. This is the line for
it. So I I won't delight. I won't ignore it.
So I I won't delight. I won't ignore it.
I won't be averse towards it. I won't
act out of it but that's it. I like if I
feel entitled for it to not be here. Oh
I am
I'm involved with it.
Yeah. Which means my mind is not turned
away from these things because I still
feel the need the necessity to deal with
it. Crossing that line
as I get a simil going out chasing
people that in front of the no no
I'm safe in here. I'm safe behind this
line. He cannot come in here.
Eternally calm.
Yeah. With the turtle, wasn't it? The turtle
With the turtle, wasn't it? The turtle
retracting its limbs until the jackal
kind of leaves.
Not like you know doing kung fu move
kung fu moves on it to to beat the
jackal up so the jackal leaves. No, you
just I can stay like this and then Jackal
I can stay like this and then Jackal
will have to lose interest in go
and that's when we speak about this
endurance endurance people seem to some
people seem to conflate that with
bearing so they translate it as enduring
but the pal isab
so that's what it means bearing means
bearing of the elements people sometimes
tend to confuse when we talk about
enduring for bearing which is at
bahhataba the pali
When we say enduring, it's really word
ki
patience. It always goes patient endurance.
It always goes patient endurance.
But the reason why I avoid patience is
because oh yeah, be patient. Just be
patient. Just it's like, well, yeah,
sure. But really think about what that
means. That means when I'm pressured by
sensual desire, do I get rid of it
because I'm impatient
or can I endure it patiently and not act
out and not cross the line? Does the
turtle What happens to a turtle if they
get if he gets impatient with the jackal
that's still not leaving?
But his arms,
it's going to have his arm snapped out.
Yeah. But so when I say enduring for I
don't know for new listeners or for
people that are still doubtful about it
take that to mean kanti in the sutas
patience and patient endurance is the
highest purification as the Buddha say
it's the highest tapas
and that's what it means doesn't mean
bahhataba of just bear it just bear the
elements just bear the sensual thought
just fight against it kind of
fight against it kind of
well that's it's already form of
fighting against you need kanti to do
bataba You need to bear elements. You
need to be patient. So basically any of
these sabas you need for
for development for abandoning for
avoiding you need to be patient first to
discern like for hindrances as we spoke
before when hindrances arise sensuality
or real will if you're habitual I I get
rid of this I think the opposite I do
this I do that you're not very patient
don't aren't you what's the problem of
I'm not welcoming this
I didn't make it arise
Why do I need to do the work of removing
it, making it go away? No, I'll just be
patient and let it go away. And when it
sees that I'm not reaching out and
interfering means it's going to lose
interest in me.
See, if I come to provoke you, you could
be or or get a reaction. I don't care
what type of reaction it's going to be.
Mara doesn't care whether you're going
to like him or hate him as long as you
give him a reaction. And that's exactly
every time when there was exactly the
description for every time in the sutas
when Mara was there attempting it's like
I'm trying I've been trying for six
seven years following him like a like a
crow just to pick on a piece of fat that
dropped out or something and there's
nothing nothing left for me to grab on.
So so he left him alone.
But that that's the only way Mara has of
of remaining unseen because
well that's the only way Mara has power
over you
if you react
if you go out in his domain. He said
that the Buddha said that says Mara does
with with people what he wants because
people take what belongs to Mara. They
go there in Mara's domain. What is the
what are the things that belong to Mara?
The old belongs to Mara. So if you
react, act, interfere, engage with the
all mara controls to that extent because
you are the one took what doesn't belong
to you.
Whereas if you're patient or you
practice this endurance,
then then it's possible to then discern
the nature of that image or that
phenomena because it's enduring.
Yeah. Having said that, I think since we
qualified that when we say endurance, we
mean kanti and people tend to confuse
that for bearing of bahhatava. It can be
other way around as well.
Sometimes people says, "Oh, this is the
ki of endurance by simply bearing random
things and expecting them to go away."
See, expecting things to go away means
you're still impatient. So, you're you
you're enduring things on physical
level. You're bearing things on physical
level. You might not be acting out, but
mentally you're not patient. You're not
accepting the fact that there is an
enduring. You're still trying to get rid
of them. And now you're using patience
as a wishful thinking.
That it will go away on its own. It will
go away on its own.
But see, you leaning towards it going
away means you're not truly patient.
You're not truly equim
towards this thing, whether it's here or
not. I don't mind. I am safe with my
limbs retracted. I am not bothered with
the fact that there is an angry person
threatening and shouting at me through
this door
because I have understood now that he
cannot cross this line.
And I understood that because I've been
patient sufficiently enough. I I endured
things on the right level sufficiently
enough. But the sign of you that you are doing
But the sign of you that you are doing
it right. It's always in the sudas that
it says his mind is elevated.
Yeah. Yeah.
And he's internally calm.
And that's another
with that thing in front of him there
with that monster there.
His mind is elevated and internally
calm. That becomes your measure
That becomes your measure
of the calmness.
The fact that I didn't have to get rid
of this thing which I used to always
think and it was bothered and I couldn't
go to sleep if he was there all day. Not
bothering me. The fact it was there was
bothering me. I I was bothering myself
with the thought of it.
Now that has not changed. Yet I am
unbothered completely unbothered things
that used to bother me.
Yeah. Among suffering he ceases to
suffer
and that's that whole like the the
elevated the kagata the onepointedness.
It just means higher place, unified
higher place.
Like there similar safety
the um like uh the river being torched
by by a flaming torch like it's
completely unaffected by or the earth
being whatever rubbish is thrown on the earth.
whatever rubbish is thrown on the earth.
It just cannot make a differenceed by
dye. Whether it whether the wind blows over
Whether it whether the wind blows over
feces or rubbish, it makes no difference
to wind.
It's and it's it's also like peripheral
awareness with this thing in front of
you. That's yeah that's kind of that
direction. That's that's that's where
your shell is the turtle. But you got
have to learn then you have to start
discerning these subtler things. Yes.
First physically and verbally is the way
of acting out and reaching towards the
jacko. But then do you cultivate the mind of oh
But then do you cultivate the mind of oh
I'm not acting towards suality but
mentally I'm happy about it.
You're not you're not enduring it.
You're already welcomed it. or uh I'm
not acting towards this aversive thing
that's in front of me but I really wish
it harm.
So it's like oh again you're not
enduring on the right level you're
you're now averse either way. Exactly.
So body speech and mind
need to be not acted out of and that's
what it means.
So if you discern that right where the
line is that um ki is the highest tapas
as the highest purification that
endurance on the right level that I keep
saying then you okay yeah that that is
protect that don't lose sight of it the
balance of it and whatever comes
sensuality ill will any of the
hindrances you will see through them and
they will not hinder you to the to to
the to whatever extent they might have
arisen it won't be hindering
Because they only hinder you when you
stepped, when you crossed the line, when
you went there,
when you got involved by body, speech or
mind. To go back to the sut about the all
To go back to the sut about the all
about um the eye and forms, the ear and
sounds and
manner, the intellect and dharmas. Um so
it's only possible really to
to discern this relationship
um if if one is secluded from sensuality
or will because
the um
yeah if one is involved in particular
sounds or particular sites or particular
phenomena and that seclusion might start by being
and that seclusion might start by being
physically withdrawn
keeping the precept guarding of the
sensors. But then that seclusion is
really developed when once you're
physically withdrawn, you have your mind
revolving around unh wholesome things.
You're not trying to get rid of it.
You're not averse towards it. You're not
welcoming it. You're actually patiently
enduring those thoughts.
So thoughts of sensuality, I must get
rid of it. No, I must not act towards
it. Why do I want to get rid of it?
Because I'm averse to the pain that he
puts on me. So I'm not patient. If there
is aversion, you're not patient. If
there is lust, there's no patience. If
there is distraction, there is no
patience. There is no endurance on the
right level. And the reason why I keep
kind of hammering this in is because a
person might think, okay, yeah, so
withdrawn from these things means I stop
I stop obviously keep precepts. I stop
acting out. Then I go into seclusion and
I stop thinking about these things and
you just it will just fall off fall. No,
no, no. That that line is discerned when
you have sure withdrawn yourself
physically from the water. But then
mentally you actually real okay but I
have no say in mano and and its own
damas in the same sense I have no say in
eyes in and the sights except restraint.
So how do you restrain the mind? How do
you make mind not think images which
when that's another image?
So that's why it's much harder as the
Buddha said to to see this mind is not
yours and to experience this passion
towards it than other things that are
inferior that more kind of coarser
because yeah you've been adhering to
you've been confusing it for your own
and so on for so long
but that's where that line is. So once
you have kept the precepts are keeping
the precepts are withdrawn uh living in
seclusion the mind will then come up
with stuff come up with upsets desires
things like that. So you deal with them
not by further taking your mind out of
it and and trying to stop thinking you
deal with it by discerning the line for
that jackal that is trying to get you
involved. which means initially you're
going to be involved and it's going to
be unpleasant and you will want to act
out of it and you will want to go and
resolve it or practice nostril
concentration to stop thinking about it
all of that because you're truly
impatient but it's like no I have been
withdrawn physically I'm guarding my
sense I'm not breaking the precepts the
virtue has been established accomplished
in I can take this pain of mind just
revolving around stuff fine let him
revolve it will have to elephant from
the jungle pin down do you think he's
just going immediately. Thank you. Yeah,
let's let's discuss what you want to
train me. I'm fully pliable right from
the start. No, it's going to try to
break and kick and scream and kill you.
But look, well, don't matter how much it
hurt, you know. No, no, no. I pin him
down. He can't break this. If I don't
choose to let him out, he can't harm me.
If I don't choose to go back to
sensuality, this mind doesn't matter how
many days. And that's why I said like
often you have to at least initially
when you say, "Oh, I'll endure things on
the right level." You have to accept the
out the worst possible scenario because
the mind will come up. Yeah, but if I
don't resolve this doubt or if I don't
resolve this upset forever it will be
like that. Yeah, I'm ready to endure it
infinitely. On that level, I shall not
ever again cross the line and interfere
with it.
If I don't transmute this uh sexual
energy, it's going I'm my head's going
to explode or something.
Fine. I will still not let the elephant
go free
until it actually calms down because all
of these are tricks and traps of a
jackal trying to get out. Yeah, but I'll
stay here forever. I better start
running. Oh, got me again. Yeah. And it
is that fear. Even minor things when you
discclusion, minor things will be little
doubts or hid
this did he mean? Three days later
did he mean? Three days later
still there. Yeah,
he meant that. And And now now I know
everything else that would have followed
which never happened. But then you
realize oh then you go and talk to that
person and he never meant that and now
it's all fine. No it's not.
It's fine in a worldly sense in an
internal sense you act it out and you
use the the reference of the jackal and
the world for where your safety is.
And that was a mistake. Now it's going
to come back again. So basically you let
the elephant go.
So now you're going to start again
by acting out of it.
By acting out of it. Yeah. So what you
want to do is recognize that such
thoughts will inevit inevitably be
amplified in solitude and you have to
accept the fact that as I said
infinitely I will endure this patiently
in that true sense of the word on the
right level and not act out of it.
That's my sole job not to cross this
line, not to open this door. And if you
have set it up through physical
withdrawal of the precepts, guarding of
the sense doors, obviously the the
speech, physical withdrawal from
company, seclusion, doesn't matter how
much your mind will doubt and all the
other hindrances, it will have to come
down. And again, that's why view is
important. If you don't see, if you
don't, if you haven't taken on faith
that it will have to come down, if you
don't necessarily haven't seen it
before, you won't do it because there is
no immediate verification. It's just
well, immediate verification is it's
getting worse. I mean, this elephant was
not this angry when I caught it, but now
it's like a different beast. Well, yeah,
that's kind of the point, but doesn't
matter the anger of the jackal. You're
going to start developing confidence in
the safety of your shell of not crossing
the line once you have stopped crossing
the line.
Then you realize oh okay yeah actually
and then it will become self-evident.
Go on. Sorry.
I was just going to say the two factors
for the arising of right view is exactly
that. The right teaching the right faith
in the teaching and then
attending to the all correctly.
Yeah. Yeah. and putting putting like
doing it in that sense
doing it repeating it cultivating it
cultivating it and if the teaching is
well expounded as it says in the sutas
as in no relevant part or the order of
development is left out
see the teaching is not well expounded
if as we said one of the first with
these group things we started doing when
I said what would you say if somebody
asked her how you how do you free from
suffering and you answered well you know an ata by
and you answered well you know an ata by
not taking self and stuff that's true
but it's not well expounded Cuz now they
would just leave with that view thinking
that's all I have to do.
Yeah. And they might do it practically, but
And they might do it practically, but
literally they're building the sixth
floor when they have no other floors
below that.
So it just won't work.
Yeah. So that's that's like that that the the
So that's that's like that that the the
gradual training and the development
they would then bring this uh endurance
on the right level to fulfillment
and then you see these principles in
concrete. I mean
that because you're experiencing
concrete safety now. See, I haven't
got rid of this mind or stop or
distracted myself or acted towards
sensuality yet. It stopped bothering me
because I I I simply were not didn't
allow acting out towards it. I didn't
try get to get rid of it. And uh as I
said, yeah, you might feel like I have
to do this forever. I have to endure
this nuisance so close to home forever.
It's like, yeah, so close to home that's
not yours.
And then you just oh so I have no right
to not to complain about it because this
doesn't belong to me
in terms of this all again
you got I and forms or sense objects and
that the bodily senses so these two
domains I
I
the forms so I'm seeing forms
and where's the eye so you got to find
and we were speaking about earlier
today. So there's these two domains
and one must be sort of countermeasured
by the other.
So if if I'm just out into the senses
sense object sorry then there's this
it's I'm tipped over there's no balance.
Yeah. But when you counter measure that
But when you counter measure that
counter way
when you know how to look at it you'll
see the other end of it.
So where's the eye? Yeah.
And then so you got these two domains
and as as I found today in this a simile
of a scales
you counter measure
and then there's that sama
he applies this and he finds that
balance and then he strives for that
to keep that balance
but that's already fully based on that's
that's what that balance is
and that's what is see is which you
attend to the front. That's generally
everyone a cigar is ionis. You're not
aware of its counterweight. You're not
aware of its womb or where it came from
so to speak. What is the opposite to
this? You're not aware of it.
Soon it's not a different way of
attending to something new.
He's just learning how to not uh overly
attend so to speak towards objects and
discern the background in regard to them
at the same time. And what else? That's
exactly the sim of the scale. It's at
the same time it's even
rather than
not too much, not too little. Yeah. Not
replace another thing, a new scale,
another thing in front of you. Doesn't
matter what you put in the front,
whether it's a different thing. The
weight of it, that's what matters.
So, how much you committed to it through
your careless attention. So all these
translations of Yoniso
u you can take them one way or the other
but they need to be qualified because
obviously it's one of the most well it's
the origin of practice really it's
person who doesn't know how to balance
their attention and I don't mean
anything mystical by that I simply mean
like seeing what else is simultaneously
there present as a background as the
root as the womb of this attention
whatever I'm attending to they won't
have any any balance to work on they
won't have any recognition of what the
middle way is no for that new book that
that I'm working on I started
translating yonikar as how do you say
concurrent concurrent attending concurrently or
concurrent attending concurrently or
concurrent attention
because simultaneous simultaneous
concurrent so yeah I'm attending to this
at the same time the experience of the
all of attending to this
the image of it
that is a background image there is a
context is seen
which is what gives this direction
so I spent years um practicing this
meditation where it was like um okay
something has arisen uh let's say some
kind of yeah angry thinking like before
and now okay I've got to just move my
attention away to the breath to the
sensations of the body
distract yourself
um and and what this is saying is is
yeah exactly like to to not get rid of
it
exactly because you get rid of it you're
not going to find the balance in regard
to it you won't find that line I'm
talking about and that's exactly that
suta that about the hindrances
the all of the five hindrances are
abandoned not by replacing them with
this or that by
such a big so every every hindrance is
an imbalance in itself
you balance them out by attending to the
womb of them
so it gives the examples like the the
hindrance of sensuality arises he
attends correctly to that weight of that
beautiful, so to speak,
and he ceases to be hindered by it. It
remains there on a scale. Not his
problem anymore.
Aversion, the the weight of the
repulsive, the weight of unenergetic, the weight of
the weight of unenergetic, the weight of
agitated,
the weight of uncertainty does not
necessarily need to become a hindrance
of a doubt if you don't lose the sight
of its counterweight. basically the
other end of it
or in a in a way like seeing it as as
something rather than being pulled by
it. So seeing so seeing ill will as ill
will as a thing. Yeah that recognizing as a
as a thing. Yeah that recognizing as a
thing there on its own arisen in all
those properties that we discussed
rather than yeah
rather than automatically just sort of
toppling over and further to get rid of
it and replace it or attend away from it
then you're then that's pulling back and
seeing it. Okay. Getting perspective. So
learning how to concurrently attend.
Yeah. To whatever has arisen.
To whatever has arisen.
Yeah. Yeah. I mean that's Yeah.
Now is it possible to go too far in the
other way? Would you then end up
mystifying the womb or
uh Well, no. Because you would you would
be unconcurrenly attending that.
You can't have too much of a balance.
No. Yeah. This is what I was trying to
get to. But could it be unbalanced in
the opposite way towards sensuality?
What would that be?
Well, yeah. Yeah. Because the opposite
way would just become another thing in
front of you. That's when I say like,
oh, okay. So, this is my experience as a
whole and the background to it is this
enduring feeling that now you made into
a foreground by overly attending to it
by not seeing it as a background to
what's in front
but by turning your attention to it.
Yeah. Yeah.
And that's why again it's it won't be
the yonisara.
Exactly. So, you can't have too much of yoniara
So, you can't have too much of yoniara
in the same sense you can't have too
much of mindfulness.
Yeah. So you kind of have too much of
the balance or this balance is too good.
That's impossible.
That's not right. That's right.
So if there is no balance means there is
no
means whatever direction there was a
relative counterweight you just made
into a new weight
so to speak.
So if you overdo it. So basically it
doesn't matter in which direction.
Doesn't matter exactly
in which you overdo it. You will end up
stucking in front of you balanced.
Yeah. You will be hindered
because you will because actually you
cannot get out. That's the whole point.
That's the whole point. All you can see
is with this this is
that's the balance. That's the way out.
That's the relinquishing of ownership.
If that site, that recognition, that
knowledge is fully developed and
unperturbable and the balance cannot be
lost.